Hello and welcome to this session of
testability improvements. My name is
Thomas and I'm joined here today by
Thaddius. We are engineers on the
Business Central team focused on
improving the developer tooling. So
let's get started.
For today's agenda, we're going to keep
it short, going to keep it to datadriven
testing and test handlers. and what that
is we'll get into in detail.
So first up datadriven testing.
Datadriven testing is not a new concept.
Um most of you probably already have
been familiar with it for a long time
but finally we have introduced it into
ALE and this allows you for having just
a single test point but with testing it
with multiple data sets. So this gives
you the flexibility of quickly uh adding
more tests by simply adding more uh data
points into your data set. And in the
era of AI features, this is so critical
that we can broaden our test um scope to
such an extent that we gain the trust uh
and confidence in our AI features. So
how we actually doing this in AL? Let's
jump into a demo. Here I have my test
code unit where I have a single test
unit in it. Um, and you can probably
already see that I have my test data set
and that's the the new attribute we
going to talk more about in a minute.
But first off, let's see how it looks
like in the interface when we start
running these tests. So right now I have
my um test right here. It hasn't been
run um but I don't see any test cases
just yet. For that I need to run the
test once and then
they will all show up here all my test
cases
and all the features that you expect
from using V studio codes test explorer
is still available for all these test
cases. So you can run a selective case
uh selective uh set of all of the test
cases. um just from those you can go in
and debug them all the regular features
that uh you come to love uh from the
test explorer.
So let's jump back into how we are
actually pulling this off in uh in in
AL. Now here I have two of these where
the first one is resource files. So if
we go over to my list of files, the
second parameter right here maps to my
resource file. And my second data source
is one that generates all of my test
cases uh on the fly. And the number here
indicates how many test cases that I
want. So if we jump into and see how the
actually implement this test data
source, then there's an interface that
we need to uh implement. It has two
functions. one that list all the test
cases and the second one where you
actually in construct all of the objects
uh with the um test context all the test
data um that you're going to run with.
And one thing to note here is the second
function right here returns an I test
context. But when we go back into the
test then we didn't see an interface of
I test context. We see my own uh tailor
made one here for the test case. And
that's allows you to make a strongly
typed interface that will give you the
uh the ease of use of working with these
test cases right here. So all of this is
gives you the the flexibility of
implementing just the data source that
you uh want and need. So right now this
reads from the resource file but it
could equally be reading from an AL
table or your web service. Um the sky's
is the limit for you here. So now with
datadriven testing we saw that it was
running in V studio code but not only
that we also give you the possibility of
running it in the AL tool and the AL MCP
uh connection.
Some of you have already seen that we
have implemented datadriven testing in
the AI test toolkit. This is not yet
using these new capabilities which means
that you are not able to run these from
Visual Studio Code. Um but that's just a
matter of time. we are planning on
migrating them to this new system. That
was all I had for datadriven testing.
That is over to you with test handlers.
>> Thank you Thomas. So now let's talk
about test handlers. So what are test
handlers? So in short, test handlers are
a way for us to provide test setup and
tear down functionality in ALE. If you
have been writing AL tests for a while,
um you'll probably know that back when
we had AL test runners, there were
triggers that you could hook into to
decide whether you should run a
particular test line or not or do some
setup material, but we sort of lost that
when we moved to the platform test
runners. Um so we've brought that back
now with test handlers and there are
several different levels of granularity
that we have. So you can specify logic
to run before or after the test code
unit runs or before and after a test
procedure or even with a new datadriven
test. You can have logic that executes
before and after the datadriven tests.
And this allows you to do things like
set up the prerequisites for your test
to set up some common records so that
you're not duplicating them across the
different test lines. Um or you can do
more global things as well because we
have two different types of test
handlers. We have the regular test
handlers which I think of as like optin
test handlers. The test code unit has to
declare that it wants to use this
particular test handler. But we also
have these default test handlers uh or I
like to think of them as global test
handlers because they run on every
single um test. And the good thing about
these default test handlers is that it
allows you to set up things like
telemetry logic or if you're let's say
extending some of our Microsoft features
and you want to um verify that your
feature you know does not break any of
the common functionality that Microsoft
provides. You can add additional setup
in these default test handlers and then
run a Microsoft test suite so you can
get more coverage that way. So let's
have a look at what these test handlers
look like in AL. The first thing you
need to do when you're defining a test
handler is that you need to register it
with the system. This sort of tells the
platform that um these test handlers are
available for test cases to hook into.
And here you can see I have two enum
extensions. The first one is extending
just the regular test handler enum and
these are the optin test handlers. And
the second one is extending the default
test handler enum and these are the ones
that I was talking about earlier saying
that these are the global test handlers.
So for this specific test handler down
here this telemetry test handler this
will be run on every single test right.
So whether it's provided in this app or
it could even be in other apps like you
know they will be run and uh but these
ones these have to be opt in by the code
unit itself. So let's have a look first
at what this interface actually is. This
itest handler interface. Um and it's
basically a bunch of hooks for you to
implement before and after logic on the
different granularity levels that I
mentioned earlier. So here you have the
on before after code unit and you have
one for the procedure level and you have
another one for the test case level. One
thing to note here is that a lot of
these have well all of these have
default implementations. This means that
you know if you if you're writing a test
handler and it only needs to execute
before or after a test code unit, you
can just implement the before after test
code unit and you don't have to
implement the rest. So that makes the
implementation simpler. So let's have a
look at one of these tests here. So um
on test code units now there's this new
property called test handlers and this
is where you register your test handler
and you can have this is a comma
separated list. So you can have multiple
um test handlers here. Um
one interesting pattern you can use. So
you might find that a lot of your test
handlers uh you might only need it for a
specific test code unit. So you can also
have the test code unit itself implement
the itest handler interface and then
just register that as a test handler. Um
and you know so this keeps your setup
and tear down logic very close to your
test code.
So one thing to keep in mind is that
these um test handlers are separate from
the test toolkit events that are driven
by AL test runners. So if you um are
writing AL test now you may be familiar
that we have a bunch of events that the
test toolkit itself uh emits and that
you can sort of like listen to and this
is separate from that. So um if you're
using those you will need to migrate
across to this if you want to take
advantage of these functionalities. Um
the other thing is that test handlers
similar to the triggers we had on the
testr runner level on the AL test
runners prior to this um you can use
test handlers to also skip certain test
cases. So you can use uh so one common
use case nowadays for us internally is
we use it for managing token
consumption. So you might want to say
hey u I want you know I have this global
test handler that monitors what is my
token consumption for the month and if
I've exceeded that limit I don't want to
run these test cases because I know that
they will consume more AI credits that's
one use case and you know there might be
other um resources that you might want
to manage and you can use test handlers
for that
and with that uh that concludes this
presentation on the testability
improvements in AL Um, I hope you enjoy
using them. I hope uh that this brings
more productivity to you and your org.
Um, as always, like you can always reach
out to us if you have bugs or any
suggestions on the Microsoft AL public
GitHub. Um, and with that, I want to say
thank you and I hope that you have
enjoyed this presentation.